<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Juan Elosua</title><link href="https://www.juanelosua.com/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://www.juanelosua.com/feeds/all.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://www.juanelosua.com/</id><updated>2015-08-03T01:00:00+02:00</updated><entry><title>Fellowship midpoint</title><link href="https://www.juanelosua.com/posts/fellowship/fellowship-midpoint/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2015-08-03T01:00:00+02:00</updated><author><name>Juan Elosua</name></author><id>tag:www.juanelosua.com,2015-08-03:posts/fellowship/fellowship-midpoint/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;It's shocking to think that half of my fellowship is gone already. It's been five months since I arrived to Buenos Aires and went to La Nación for the first time with butterflies on my stomach, not sure what to expect and how would I feel working in a newsroom.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So what's it like to be a Knight-Mozilla fellow? How do you interact with the rest of the newsroom? What's special about being a developer working inside a newsroom? How do you handle time management? &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this post I will try to answer some of those questions as well as make some reflections about my fellowship so far. The timeframe to postulate to become a 2016 Knight-Mozilla fellow is &lt;a href="https://opennews.org/what/fellowships/apply/"&gt;open&lt;/a&gt; until the 21st of August so I hope this post will help push some of the undecided into submitting their application... you won't regret it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;h2 id="working-in-a-newsroom-as-a-developer"&gt;Working in a newsroom as a developer?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3 id="impact-on-society"&gt;Impact on society&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I joined the data journalism world I was looking for a field that would help me have an impact on society. Working in a newsroom has that potential, most of us get to know what is going on in  the outside world through news, whether the information comes from social networks, through traditional newspapers or online sites. This fact comes with two readings:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The projects that you develop inside a newsroom are going to hit a big audience, giving you the chance to try to improve those parts of the &lt;em&gt;status quo&lt;/em&gt; that are not functioning as they should. Sometimes it allows you to capture attention on an important matter that is buried in a pile of &lt;em&gt;boring&lt;/em&gt; official reports that we all have at our disposal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With big audience comes big responsibility. You should work hard to deliver content that is understandable and not geared towards a particular point of view. Thankfully today's tools let you empower readers to interact and explore news apps leveraging some of the pressure from our shoulders. Also, technically, you are pushed to the limit in terms of performance requirements.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h3 id="multidisciplinary-teams"&gt;Multidisciplinary teams&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think that interdisciplinary teams are going to become more and more needed for modern enterprises to succeed in this fast-paced ever changing world we are living on. In that sense data journalism blends naturally with that need since the normal team has a variety of profiles ranging from journalists to designers, developers, or even mathematicians or statisticians if you are lucky.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The added value that comes out of teams with such different backgrounds is rich when you are careful enough to listen to every member of the team and make them part of the project from the very beginning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="one-baby-each-day"&gt;One baby each day&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even if you are not working on breaking news, as it's my case, the atmosphere that you live has that special rhythm. Not many industries have to deliver a product each day, so &lt;em&gt;the cycle of life&lt;/em&gt; is short, thrilling and sometimes stressful, but always exciting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From a developer point of view, working in a deadline based development changes your way of thinking. Most of us are really perfectionists at heart and would like our projects to be state of the art projects that use the best architecture and software pattern designs... But if you have to have it done by 10pm, then some of the out-of-core functionality is just not going to happen and you need to focus on what can be done.   &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="training-as-a-networking-tool"&gt;Training as a networking tool&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="trainer" class="post_left" src="/images/fellowship/trainer.jpg" width="40%" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When embedded in a large newsroom, sometimes it's hard to get to know the rest of the organization and find &lt;em&gt;allies&lt;/em&gt; to push projects forward from an editorial point of view. I have used training as an strategy to connect with interested people inside the newsroom and that has helped me feel more integrated at La Nación.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I love training, since it helps you clarify your own ideas when you need to get them out of your brain and explain them to someone else. We do not have time to learn all the things we would like so sharing knowledge is a key piece to self-improvement today, both as a trainer or as a trainee.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="clear_float"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3 id="exclusives-vs-opensource"&gt;Exclusives vs. OpenSource&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="boxing" class="post_right" src="/images/fellowship/boxing.jpg" width="40%" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the main interesting conflicts you can live as a fellow is the exclusive vs. opensource battle. Being part of a community driven effort such as Mozilla you are used to and expected to work in the open, sharing code and documentation that would be helpful for the community. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sometimes, the openness we all look forward to, finds an opponent force in the form of news exclusives or reluctances of the newsrooms to share their assets with their competitors. After all newsrooms are private businesses that need to generate revenue if they want to survive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I found timing to be a good way to keep everybody happy. We have developed projects to cover election results in Argentina, and after being published, we have worked on the documentation and code cleaning needed to release them as an open source project.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="clear_float"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;h2 id="projects"&gt;Projects&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The main reason why I applied for the fellowship was that, even though I had been working in the surroundings of newsrooms, through training and some NGO projects (&lt;a href="http://www.civio.es/en"&gt;Civio&lt;/a&gt;), I wanted to be embedded in an actual newsroom. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Therefore, in my case, it was obvious that my main focus would be to work with the rest of the newsroom teams in their projects and try to add value with my skills.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since the begining of my fellowship I have worked in a wide variety of projects inside La Nación: scraping some information out of government pages, adapting a ProPublica timeline tool in order to use it in a &lt;a href="http://casos.lanacion.com.ar/indec-la-maquina-de-la-mentira"&gt;storytelling&lt;/a&gt;, and last but not the least, I have been working on elections apps... 2015 is a big election year in Argentina.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.lanacion.com.ar/1809205-cayo-el-caudal-de-votos-de-pro-en-el-78-de-las-escuelas" target="_blank"&gt;&lt;img alt="polling station map" class="post_left_together" src="/images/fellowship/polling.jpg" width="48%" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="http://casos.lanacion.com.ar/indec-la-maquina-de-la-mentira" target="_blank"&gt;&lt;img alt="INDEC timeline" class="post_right_together" src="/images/fellowship/INDEC.png" width="48%" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="clear_float"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Take a look at &lt;a href="https://github.com/lanacioncom/"&gt;La Nacion's github&lt;/a&gt; for more information on the projects and the code.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;h2 id="conferences"&gt;Conferences&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another part of the fellowship is attending and speaking at conferences. This can be challenging if you are a shy person but it is a needed step in order to get you out of your comfort zone and getting to know other interesting people in the community.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="conference" class="post_full" src="/images/fellowship/conference.jpg" width="90%" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="clear_float"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a list of the conferences I have attended in this five months period:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Fellowship on boarding event (Los Angeles - January 2015)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;NICAR 2015 (Atlanta - March 2015)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Jornadas de periodismo de datos OKNF España (Madrid &amp;amp; Barcelona - June 2015)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;SRCCON  (Minneapolis - June 2015)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Dato Conference (San Francisco - July 2015)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Opennews code convening (Portland - July 2015)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;h2 id="main-struggles"&gt;Main struggles&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let me share with you my main two struggles as a fellow so far.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="impostor-syndrome"&gt;Impostor Syndrome&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I remember the feeling, when applying to the fellowship after reading previous fellows profiles, I thought I was not qualified to be one of them... but guess what, I was wrong... here I am. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Often, what you get from the never ending flow of information we receive each day are finished awesome products. You can feel that if would take you a year to develop those things, and it seems that everybody else can deliver them in a blink of an eye.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was impressed/relieved by my fellowship cohort when we got together for the onboarding in Los Angeles realising that many of us had the same feeling. I guess my point is: you should apply and let Opennews decide if you are qualified or not. They know better!! they want to bring variety to newsrooms and maybe your strengths fit perfectly in what they are searching for a particular candidate newsroom.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I still feel that I could be more productive, maybe that is just a part of my perfectionist personality and the continuous learning field I wanted to join. Anyhow, one of the reasons why I left my comfort zone in the banking industry some years ago was that I wanted to be surrounded by people that I admire and I can learn from. The data journalism community has been really welcoming and friendly and has helped me to make that transition.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="time-management"&gt;Time management &lt;img alt="clock" class="post_left" src="/images/fellowship/clock2.jpg" width="40%" /&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The other main struggle when I look back at these five months is time management. Traveling and attending to conferences bites quite a part of your time as a fellow, working in a newsroom is demanding and sometimes you do not find the time to work on side projects that you are interested in.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I decided I needed one day off the newsroom buzz so I can focus on other projects or tasks that I needed to complete. I've talked to my newsroom point of contact, and normally I spend friday's working from home so that I can find the time to do some not-newsroom related work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="clear_float"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;h2 id="summary"&gt;Summary&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="fellows" class="post_right" src="/images/fellowship/fellows.png" width="40%" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Being a fellow is just an overall great experience full of excitement, work, travel, conferences and meeting interesting people. You can devote time to dig in those projects that you did not find the time to address but you think will have a great impact on our society.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The team at Opennews is just great, they are comprehensive, they give you the freedom to pursue your dream projects and serve as a encyclopedia in terms of connecting you with the right persons to push those projects forward.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are unsure about what your fellowship experience could be, it's definitely worthwhile to take a look also at what other 2015 fellows experiences have been in their own words: &lt;a href="(http://livialabate.com/says/so-you-think-you-can-dance/)"&gt;Livia Labate&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="http://spaceandtim.es/opennews/fellowship_status"&gt;Francis Tseng&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="http://blog.kavyasukumar.com/paging-developers-to-newsrooms/"&gt;Kavya Sukumar&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Trust me, you should &lt;a href="https://opennews.org/what/fellowships/apply/"&gt;apply&lt;/a&gt;. If you have any doubts, just ping me on &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/jjelosua"&gt;twitter&lt;/a&gt; and I will be happy to talk through them.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="opennews"></category></entry><entry><title>2015 PASO CABA Elections</title><link href="https://www.juanelosua.com/posts/fellowship/2015pasocaba/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2015-05-10T13:20:00+02:00</updated><author><name>Juan Elosua</name></author><id>tag:www.juanelosua.com,2015-05-10:posts/fellowship/2015pasocaba/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;On April 26th Buenos Aires has held its first PASO elections. PASO stands for Simultaneous and Obligatory Open Primary elections. In this election two main things are decided:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Which candidate will pass as the official candidate for each political party for the final elections&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Each political party has to achieve at least 1.5% of the total votes to be able to continue on the election race.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These were my first elections inside a newsroom and it was thrilling!! It was like being inside a movie surrounded by journalists waiting for the initial results to rush to their computers to write articles and analysis... but we needed data and I can tell you it was not easy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This 2015 will be a year full of elections: Regional PASO elections, Regional final elections and the mother of all... Presidential elections.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Calendar" class="post_left" src="/images/2015_paso_caba/calendar.jpg" width="48%" /&gt;In Argentina voting is a compulsory right, so Argentinians will be voting many times during this year. One of the first things that stroke me as a foreigner is that PASO elections are not withheld inside the political party affiliates but rather extended to the whole census. In Spain Primary elections only affect the affiliates and thus are rather overlooked by the overall population. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have had some interesting discussions on whether extending Primary elections to the overall population is a good democratic procedure... on one hand it always seems a good idea to let people decide the candidate that they want for their party of choice...but on the other hand having such a low barrier for making the cut for the next round would theoretically allow "big" parties to try to tweak the results of their other contestants by asking their loyal voters to vote for the other party weak candidate...kind of convoluted but possible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The local government decided to switch technological providers for this and upcoming elections and as usual there is some adjustment time to get things working smoothly. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At La Nación, we wanted to make a news app that would allow readers to perform realtime analysis of the results of the elections showing as many details as possible, therefore we wanted to show the results by polling station.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="frontend-isolation"&gt;Frontend isolation&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Due to the mentioned technical change the local government was running late in providing newsrooms with details on how the results were going to be made available during the realtime vote counting process.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So we decided that we needed to &lt;em&gt;blackbox&lt;/em&gt; the frontend needs and specify a data format that was required by the frontend leaving the transformation tasks to the backend and assuming that it was going to be doable after all.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That way we could move forward in defining the final visualizations and the different reader interaction capabilities and drilldown analysis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="clear_float"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;h2 id="backend-nightmare"&gt;Backend nightmare&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="API" class="post_right" src="/images/2015_paso_caba/API.jpg" width="48%" /&gt; After being really persuasive with government officials, we ended up having some documentation on the 21st of April... we were going to have an API to query but not many details yet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We started defining the backend structure out of thin air, trying to be modular so that we could be efficient when changes were necessary.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Trying to divide the functionality in modules helps when you find an error, because you can easily go directly to the module that is causing the error and correct it. But on the other hand, it results in more difficulties in keeping the state of the overall process simple enough. We relied on &lt;a href="https://docs.python.org/2/tutorial/errors.html#user-defined-exceptions" target="_blank"&gt;User-Defined Exceptions&lt;/a&gt; to keep track of the overall process while executing code in a module deep down the execution stack.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We did not have data yet to test the process so we developed an adhoc simulation script that would randomly produce voting results distributions. My wife to the rescue... &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/marta_alonso_f"&gt;Marta&lt;/a&gt; helped us develop the results simulation and I believe that was a key decision in the overall success of the project since it allowed us to start testing the backend well ahead of the API availability.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally we were given an endpoint to test the government API by friday 24th at 18h... fun weekend ahead. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="clear_float"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;h2 id="logging-what-the-h-is-going-on"&gt;Logging: What the h...  is going on!!!&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Postman" class="post_right" src="/images/2015_paso_caba/log.jpg" width="48%" /&gt;As a realtime application (running on EC2 machines) we knew that it was almost as important to have an easy way to keep track of what was going on in the backend on realtime to be able to act quickly in case something unexpected happened.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We developed a logging strategy that was published each time the process was run (each minute), making it accessible through HTTP.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For monitoring purposes we used &lt;a href="https://chrome.google.com/webstore/detail/postman-rest-client-packa/fhbjgbiflinjbdggehcddcbncdddomop?hl=en" target="_blank"&gt;Postman&lt;/a&gt;, a chrome app that lets you define and save collections of HTTP requests:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;One collection for the government API endpoints&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;One collection for the backend monitoring &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;div class="clear_float"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;h2 id="concurrency-100000-simultaneous-visitors"&gt;Concurrency &amp;gt;100.000 simultaneous visitors&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Being a freelance developer that used to work with NGOs in Spain to increase transparency and the use of Open Data I had not being exposed to the traffic that the homepage of La Nación receives on an election day. So It was really interesting for me to learn from the infrastructure and architecture team the tips &amp;amp; tricks that we needed to take into account in order to be successful: HTTP caches, Content Delivery Networks configuration and static files versioning... All of that was new to me, but really important in terms of performance and bug fixing on the fly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To be able to handle that, we decided that we needed an "almost" automatic way of deployment that would decrease the probabilities of human errors while going through a somewhat stressful situation. We used &lt;a href="http://gulpjs.com/" target="_blank"&gt;&lt;em&gt;gulp&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; to automate the deployment process, letting it handle the minification, uglyfying and versioning for us. Extract of the gulp deployment process:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span class="nx"&gt;gulp&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nx"&gt;task&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s1"&gt;&amp;#39;minify-css&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="kd"&gt;function&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;()&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="nx"&gt;gulp&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nx"&gt;src&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;([&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s1"&gt;&amp;#39;css/reset.css&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s1"&gt;&amp;#39;css/fonts.css&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; 
          &lt;span class="s1"&gt;&amp;#39;css/select2.css&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s1"&gt;&amp;#39;css/style.css&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;],&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;{&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nx"&gt;cwd&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s1"&gt;&amp;#39;../webapp&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;})&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="p"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nx"&gt;pipe&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nx"&gt;minifyCSS&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;())&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="p"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nx"&gt;pipe&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nx"&gt;concat&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nx"&gt;css_file_min&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;))&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="p"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nx"&gt;pipe&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nx"&gt;gulp&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nx"&gt;dest&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s1"&gt;&amp;#39;../build/css&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;));&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="p"&gt;});&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class="nx"&gt;gulp&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nx"&gt;task&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s1"&gt;&amp;#39;test_js&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="kd"&gt;function&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(){&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="k"&gt;return&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nx"&gt;gulp&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nx"&gt;src&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;([&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s1"&gt;&amp;#39;js/permanentlinkjs.js&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s1"&gt;&amp;#39;js/handlebars_helpers.js&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
                     &lt;span class="s1"&gt;&amp;#39;js/elecciones_app.js&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s1"&gt;&amp;#39;js/scripts.js&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;],&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;{&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nx"&gt;cwd&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s1"&gt;&amp;#39;../webapp&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;})&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class="p"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nx"&gt;pipe&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nx"&gt;jshint&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;())&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class="p"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nx"&gt;pipe&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nx"&gt;jshint&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nx"&gt;reporter&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s1"&gt;&amp;#39;default&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;))&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class="p"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nx"&gt;pipe&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nx"&gt;jshint&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nx"&gt;reporter&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nx"&gt;stylish&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;));&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="p"&gt;});&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class="nx"&gt;gulp&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nx"&gt;task&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s1"&gt;&amp;#39;js&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s1"&gt;&amp;#39;test_js&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;],&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="kd"&gt;function&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;()&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="kd"&gt;var&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nx"&gt;all&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nx"&gt;gulp&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nx"&gt;src&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;([&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s1"&gt;&amp;#39;js/permanentlinkjs.js&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s1"&gt;&amp;#39;js/handlebars_helpers.js&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
                       &lt;span class="s1"&gt;&amp;#39;js/elecciones_app.js&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s1"&gt;&amp;#39;js/scripts.js&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;]&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;{&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nx"&gt;cwd&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s1"&gt;&amp;#39;../webapp&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;})&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class="p"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nx"&gt;pipe&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nx"&gt;sourcemaps&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nx"&gt;init&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;())&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class="p"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nx"&gt;pipe&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nx"&gt;uglify&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;())&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class="p"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nx"&gt;pipe&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nx"&gt;concat&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nx"&gt;js_all&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;))&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class="p"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nx"&gt;pipe&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nx"&gt;sourcemaps&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nx"&gt;write&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s1"&gt;&amp;#39;./&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;))&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class="p"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nx"&gt;pipe&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nx"&gt;gulp&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nx"&gt;dest&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s1"&gt;&amp;#39;../build/js&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;));&lt;/span&gt;

    &lt;span class="kd"&gt;var&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nx"&gt;vendor&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nx"&gt;gulp&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nx"&gt;src&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;([&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class="s1"&gt;&amp;#39;libs/jquery/dist/jquery.min.js&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; 
        &lt;span class="s1"&gt;&amp;#39;libs/select2/select2.min.js&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; 
        &lt;span class="s1"&gt;&amp;#39;libs/handlebars/handlebars.min.js&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; 
        &lt;span class="s1"&gt;&amp;#39;libs/jquery.nicescroll/jquery.nicescroll.min.js&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; 
        &lt;span class="p"&gt;],&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;{&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nx"&gt;cwd&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s1"&gt;&amp;#39;../webapp&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;})&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class="p"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nx"&gt;pipe&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nx"&gt;sourcemaps&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nx"&gt;init&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;())&lt;/span&gt;
          &lt;span class="p"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nx"&gt;pipe&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nx"&gt;uglify&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;())&lt;/span&gt;
          &lt;span class="p"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nx"&gt;pipe&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nx"&gt;concat&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nx"&gt;js_vendor&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;))&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class="p"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nx"&gt;pipe&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nx"&gt;sourcemaps&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nx"&gt;write&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s1"&gt;&amp;#39;./&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;))&lt;/span&gt;
          &lt;span class="p"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nx"&gt;pipe&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nx"&gt;gulp&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nx"&gt;dest&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s1"&gt;&amp;#39;../build/libs&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;));&lt;/span&gt;

    &lt;span class="k"&gt;return&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nx"&gt;merge&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nx"&gt;all&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nx"&gt;vendor&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class="p"&gt;});&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class="nx"&gt;gulp&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nx"&gt;task&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s1"&gt;&amp;#39;copy&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="kd"&gt;function&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;()&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="kd"&gt;var&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nx"&gt;opts&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class="nx"&gt;conditionals&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="kc"&gt;true&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class="nx"&gt;spare&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="kc"&gt;true&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="p"&gt;};&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="kd"&gt;var&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nx"&gt;html&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nx"&gt;gulp&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nx"&gt;src&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s1"&gt;&amp;#39;*.html&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;{&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nx"&gt;cwd&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s1"&gt;&amp;#39;../webapp&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;})&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class="p"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nx"&gt;pipe&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nx"&gt;htmlreplace&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;({&lt;/span&gt;
            &lt;span class="nx"&gt;js&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s1"&gt;&amp;#39;libs/&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;+&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nx"&gt;js_vendor&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s1"&gt;&amp;#39;js/&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;+&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nx"&gt;js_all&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;],&lt;/span&gt;
            &lt;span class="nx"&gt;css&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s1"&gt;&amp;#39;css/&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;+&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nx"&gt;css_file_min&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;]&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class="p"&gt;}))&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class="p"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nx"&gt;pipe&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nx"&gt;minifyHTML&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nx"&gt;opts&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;))&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class="p"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nx"&gt;pipe&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nx"&gt;gulp&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nx"&gt;dest&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s1"&gt;&amp;#39;../build&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;));&lt;/span&gt;


    &lt;span class="kd"&gt;var&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nx"&gt;fonts&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nx"&gt;gulp&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nx"&gt;src&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s1"&gt;&amp;#39;css/fonts/*&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;{&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nx"&gt;cwd&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s1"&gt;&amp;#39;../webapp&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;})&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class="p"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nx"&gt;pipe&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nx"&gt;gulp&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nx"&gt;dest&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s1"&gt;&amp;#39;../build/css/fonts&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;));&lt;/span&gt;

    &lt;span class="kd"&gt;var&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nx"&gt;img&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nx"&gt;gulp&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nx"&gt;src&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s1"&gt;&amp;#39;img/*&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;{&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nx"&gt;cwd&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s1"&gt;&amp;#39;../webapp&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;})&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class="p"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nx"&gt;pipe&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nx"&gt;gulp&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nx"&gt;dest&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s1"&gt;&amp;#39;../build/img&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;));&lt;/span&gt;

    &lt;span class="kd"&gt;var&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nx"&gt;css_img&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nx"&gt;gulp&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nx"&gt;src&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;([&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s1"&gt;&amp;#39;css/images/*&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;],&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;{&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nx"&gt;cwd&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s1"&gt;&amp;#39;../webapp&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;})&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class="p"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nx"&gt;pipe&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nx"&gt;gulp&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nx"&gt;dest&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s1"&gt;&amp;#39;../build/css/images&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;));&lt;/span&gt;

    &lt;span class="kd"&gt;var&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nx"&gt;data&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nx"&gt;gulp&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nx"&gt;src&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s1"&gt;&amp;#39;data/*&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;{&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nx"&gt;cwd&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s1"&gt;&amp;#39;../webapp&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;})&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class="p"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nx"&gt;pipe&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nx"&gt;gulp&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nx"&gt;dest&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s1"&gt;&amp;#39;../build/data&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;));&lt;/span&gt;

    &lt;span class="k"&gt;return&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nx"&gt;merge&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nx"&gt;html&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nx"&gt;fonts&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nx"&gt;img&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nx"&gt;css_img&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nx"&gt;data&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="p"&gt;});&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class="nx"&gt;gulp&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nx"&gt;task&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s1"&gt;&amp;#39;build&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s1"&gt;&amp;#39;minify-css&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s1"&gt;&amp;#39;js&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s1"&gt;&amp;#39;copy&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;]);&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;h2 id="realtime-news-app"&gt;Realtime news app&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the end, on the election day, we were "anxious" to check if the kind of creative way of connecting the dots was going to work out... and it did!!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After sometime while the API was not responding we were able to get a full response to our backend and transform it to the frontend expected format... that was at 22:30 Sunday night... we even published the initial results before the official government page that was suffering from availability issues.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We have cleaned up after ourselves and have released the code of the project on github &lt;a href="https://github.com/lanacioncom/elecciones_2015_caba"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.lanacion.com.ar/1787651-elecciones-2015-resultados-de-las-paso-portenas-en-un-mapa-interactivo" target="_blank"&gt;&lt;img alt="Realtime map" class="post_left_together" src="/images/2015_paso_caba/realtime.jpg" width="48%" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="http://www.lanacion.com.ar/1787653-en-vivo-como-se-perfilan-los-ganadores-y-perdedores-de-las-paso-portenas" target="_blank"&gt;&lt;img alt="Realtime ranking" class="post_right_together" src="/images/2015_paso_caba/quienesquien.jpg" width="48%" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="clear_float"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;h2 id="calm-after-the-storm-nope"&gt;Calm after the storm... Nope!!&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After the adrenaline came down a bit we realized that had not completed our task since we wanted to let the readers go deep into their local details... we needed the results by polling station.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Luckily &lt;a href="http://jazzido.com/"&gt;Manuel Aristarán&lt;/a&gt; had worked on a similar project for the 2013 elections and we had worked in advance to obtain the geolocation of each polling station. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thanks to that we could delivered a map that showed the results for each polling station the same day we got the official results from the Buenos Aires Government.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.lanacion.com.ar/1788681-como-fueron-los-resultados-de-las-paso-en-la-escuela-donde-votaste" target="_blank"&gt;&lt;img alt="polling station results" class="post_full" src="/images/2015_paso_caba/polling_station.jpg" width="90%" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We used &lt;a href="http://docs.cartodb.com/cartodb-platform/cartodb-js.html" target="_blank"&gt;&lt;em&gt;cartodb.js&lt;/em&gt; API&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="http://requirejs.org/" target="_blank"&gt;&lt;em&gt;require.js&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; in order to keep the javascript development modular. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To avoid having too many HTTP requests we finally integrated the requirejs optimizer into the gulp deployment pipeline so that we have the benefit of modularity in development but with a nice performance on production.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://github.com/lanacioncom/2015_paso_caba_map" target="_blank"&gt;Here&lt;/a&gt; is the open sourced code for that map.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="clear_float"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;h2 id="wrap-up"&gt;Wrap up&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Team" class="post_right" src="/images/2015_paso_caba/team.jpg" width="48%" /&gt;I am really grateful for being able to have lived the election experience inside a newsroom. We have worked hard as a team and the overall results were really positive... really proud of the team and the effort.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thanks to the rest of the team &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/cbertelegni"&gt;Cristian Bertelegni&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/gasgas83"&gt;Gaston de la Llana&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/ploscri"&gt;Pablo Loscri&lt;/a&gt; for keeping such a nice working atmosphere. I would also like to send special thanks to Flor Fernández and Mariana Trigo for their support.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is worth mentioning that all this work and analysis was not only used in the online edition at La Nación. The results from the developed &lt;em&gt;News Apps&lt;/em&gt; were also used to enrich the reader experience on the paper edition. That means a double win for the newsroom: creating an interactive application that will also generate value on the printed version.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="paper edition" class="post_full" src="/images/2015_paso_caba/paper.jpg" width="100%" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="clear_float"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</summary><category term="opennews"></category><category term="elections"></category></entry><entry><title>2015 Nicar conference</title><link href="https://www.juanelosua.com/posts/event/nicar2015/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2015-03-17T13:20:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Juan Elosua</name></author><id>tag:www.juanelosua.com,2015-03-17:posts/event/nicar2015/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://ire.org/conferences/nicar2015/"&gt;Nicar2015&lt;/a&gt; in Atlanta was my first conference as a Knight-Mozilla fellow and it was a fantastic experience. More than 1,000 people from the journalism &amp;amp; desgin &amp;amp; technology fields gather for an intensive stint of 4-5 days with hands-on sessions, panels and demos on tools to innovate in Computer Assisted Journalism.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the first things that you realize once you get there is that you are going to have a feeling of missing out no matter how hard you try. There are over 10 simultaneous sessions and unless you can clone yourself (tried that but didn't work...) you need to carefully choose the sessions that you think you can take more profit from.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Atlanta" class="post_left_together" src="/images/nicar2015/Atlanta.jpg" width="48%" /&gt; &lt;img alt="Nicar" class="post_right_together" src="/images/nicar2015/NicarEvolution.jpg" width="48%" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let me go through some of the sessions that I have enjoyed the most, but before that, I will point you to a really useful resource &lt;a href="http://blog.chryswu.com/2015/02/20/nicar-2015-slides-links-tutorials/" target="_blank"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; curated by &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/MacDiva"&gt;@MacDiva&lt;/a&gt; for you to dive in the session slides that are more aligned with your field of interest.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I can divide the sessions that had more impact on me in two subgroups: technical and management oriented. Here are my favorites:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="clear_float"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;h2 id="management-oriented-sessions"&gt;Management oriented sessions&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3 id="do-it-once-and-only-once"&gt;Do it once and only once&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Do It Once" class="post_right" src="/images/nicar2015/DoItOnce.png" width="50%" /&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Speakers: &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/derekwillis"&gt;Derek Willis&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; &amp;amp; &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/eads"&gt;David Eaves&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Derek and David warned us about the time wasting perils of data processing without automation and audit trails.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the highlights of the talk to me was finding out about &lt;a href="https://github.com/benbalter/change_agent" target="_blank"&gt;Ben Balter change agent&lt;/a&gt;: A Git-backed key-value store, for tracking changes to documents and other files over time as defined by Ben in the repo.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I always thought that version control will be applied to other industries outside technology soon, and that is going to be a changemaker in that industry.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Slides: &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href="http://dwillis.github.io/do-it-once-nicar-2015/"&gt;Derek Slides&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; &amp;amp; &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href="http://recoveredfactory.net/cleaner-data-nicar15/"&gt;David Slides&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="processes-standards-and-documentation-for-data-driven-projects"&gt;Processes, standards and documentation for data-driven projects&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Christopher Groskopf" class="post_right" src="/images/nicar2015/ChristopherTip.png" width="50%" /&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Speakers: &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/onyxfish"&gt;Christopher Groskopf&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; &amp;amp; &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/poverberg"&gt;Paul Overberg&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this session Paul and Christopher walked us through the importance of creating team standards, project vocabularies and consistent procedures to produce high quality projects in a sustainable way. This is specially crucial when working under a deadline, something that happens naturally in newsrooms.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In particular, I found Christopher's part full of wisdom. Coming from someone that has worked in newsrooms and remotely for a while and that has taken the time to share his experience in this invaluable &lt;a href="http://recoveredfactory.net/cleaner-data-nicar15/" target="_blank"&gt;tips&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="clear_float"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;h2 id="technical-sessions"&gt;Technical sessions&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3 id="from-text-to-pictures"&gt;From text to pictures&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Text Visualization inspiration" class="post_right" src="/images/nicar2015/TextPipeline.jpg" width="50%" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Speakers: &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.nickdiakopoulos.com/"&gt;Nicholas Diakopoulos&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On thursday I had a really good start with a session on how to handle and interpret big amounts of text through visualization by Nicholas Diakopoulos. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nicholas explored different approaches on analizing texts and visualing the content or even the structure to get an insight of what is hidden in that pile of data, after all text is data right?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But Nicholas pointed out that text is data but with a particular behavior, the order in which words appear is important to the meaning of a sentence and you need to take that into account.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He also talked about the necessary text processing pipeline in order to get a useful analysis&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Initial text&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Lowercase&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Tokenize&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Stem&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Stop Word Removal.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Slides: &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href="http://t.co/kfqbTBzjI6"&gt;Nicholas Slides&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="plotly"&gt;Plot.ly&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Plotly" class="post_right" src="/images/nicar2015/Plotly.png" width="50%" /&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Speakers: &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.linkedin.com/pub/matt-sundquist/30/800/752"&gt;Matthew Sundquist&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Until NICAR I had not heard about plot.ly (yeah I know...shame on me!!) and I think that it has a lot of potential in the data journalism field and ranging from journalists that want to create graphs without coding to developers through their &lt;a href="https://plot.ly/api/"&gt;API&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It generates D3.js visualizations under the hood but it exposes many ways to perform an integration with the platform.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To find out more just check their &lt;a href="https://plot.ly/learn/"&gt;tutorials&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://plot.ly/api/"&gt;API documentation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="using-machine-learning-to-deal-with-dirty-data-a-dedupe-demonstration"&gt;Using machine learning to deal with dirty data: a Dedupe demonstration&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Dedupe" class="post_right" src="/images/nicar2015/Dedupe.png" width="50%" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Speakers: &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/jeffernsthausen"&gt;Jeff Ernsthausen&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/derekeder"&gt;Derek Eder&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/evanzanten"&gt;Eric van Zanten&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; &amp;amp; &lt;a href="https://github.com/fgregg"&gt;Forest Gregg&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If I had to pick my favorite session from this year's conference I would have to choose the demo on a tool developed by datamade called &lt;a href="https://github.com/datamade/dedupe"&gt;Dedupe&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is a machine learning based python library for accurate and scalable data deduplication and entity-resolution. I have fought many times with trying to combine different datasets that do not have a clear identifier to join by. OpenRefine can help with small datasets but the process of clustering is not repeatable and even more important it is not scalable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Having a machine learning process for that kind of task is probably the best way to go. I got so inspired by that demo that I think a big part of my fellowship is going to be focused on machine learning and how to apply it to journalistic problems. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://github.com/datamade" target="_blank"&gt;&lt;img alt="Dedupe OpenSource" class="post_full" src="/images/nicar2015/Dedupe_OSS.png" width="70%" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a starter I am going to use dedupe to try to match two different datasets for the upcoming argentinian elections, in next posts I will tell you how it went and what have I learned in the process.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="clear_float"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;h2 id="technical-tip-of-the-day"&gt;Technical tip of the day&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let's dig a little bit deeper on how to install Numpy with parallel processing support on a Mac OS X (tested on 10.9 and 10.10) you can read more about the convoluted issue &lt;a href="http://mail.scipy.org/pipermail/numpy-discussion/2012-August/063589.html"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. Since it took me a while to get things working so I thought maybe sharing my pains can help someone in the future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I will walk you through the installation process that has worked for me, if you think it can be improved don't hesitate to contact me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you have not installed homebrew, the first step is to do so:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span class="nv"&gt;$ &lt;/span&gt;ruby -e &lt;span class="s2"&gt;&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="k"&gt;$(&lt;/span&gt;curl -fsSL https://raw.githubusercontent.com/Homebrew/install/master/install&lt;span class="k"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s2"&gt;&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Set up some compilation flags on your environment of choice&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span class="nb"&gt;export &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nv"&gt;CFLAGS&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;-Qunused-arguments 
&lt;span class="nb"&gt;export &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nv"&gt;CPPFLAGS&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;-Qunused-arguments
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Brew tap the homebrew python repo&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span class="nv"&gt;$ &lt;/span&gt;brew tap homebrew/python
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Install Numpy with OpenBlas support&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span class="nv"&gt;$ &lt;/span&gt;brew install numpy --with-openblas
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Check if Numpy is linked against OpenBlas&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="kn"&gt;import&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nn"&gt;numpy&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="kn"&gt;as&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nn"&gt;np&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="o"&gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;np&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;__config__&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;show&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;()&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You should see an output like this&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;lapack_opt_info&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="n"&gt;libraries&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;&amp;#39;openblas&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s"&gt;&amp;#39;openblas&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;]&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="n"&gt;library_dirs&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;&amp;#39;/usr/local/opt/openblas/lib&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;]&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="n"&gt;language&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;f77&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="n"&gt;blas_opt_info&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="n"&gt;libraries&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;&amp;#39;openblas&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s"&gt;&amp;#39;openblas&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;]&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="n"&gt;library_dirs&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;&amp;#39;/usr/local/opt/openblas/lib&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;]&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="n"&gt;language&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;f77&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="n"&gt;openblas_info&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="n"&gt;libraries&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;&amp;#39;openblas&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s"&gt;&amp;#39;openblas&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;]&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="n"&gt;library_dirs&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;&amp;#39;/usr/local/opt/openblas/lib&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;]&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="n"&gt;language&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;f77&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="n"&gt;openblas_lapack_info&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="n"&gt;libraries&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;&amp;#39;openblas&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s"&gt;&amp;#39;openblas&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;]&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="n"&gt;library_dirs&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;&amp;#39;/usr/local/opt/openblas/lib&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;]&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="n"&gt;language&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;f77&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="n"&gt;blas_mkl_info&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class="n"&gt;NOT&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;AVAILABLE&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now you can continue with the normal installation process for dedupe, just remember to include system packages if you are going to use a virtualenv so that the compiled Numpy with OpenBlas support will be used inside the virtual environment&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span class="nv"&gt;$ &lt;/span&gt;virtualenv venv --system-site-packages
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;div class="clear_float"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;h2 id="wrap-up"&gt;Wrap up&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This year's NICAR conference in Atlanta was overall a great experience, It has guided me towards machine learning as a focus for my fellowship year. I think this technique will become more and more adopted by newsrooms in the following years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have met many people with my same interests (is always good not to feel alone... ;-)). I also had the opportunity to get to chat more with the 2015 knight-mozilla fellows cohort and also spend sometime with other fellows from past years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I would recommend anyone interested in the data journalism field to at least attend once to this conference organized by &lt;a href="http://ire.org/about/"&gt;Investigative Reporters &amp;amp; Editors&lt;/a&gt; you will not regret it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="clear_float"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</summary><category term="opennews"></category></entry><entry><title>2015 Knight-Mozilla fellowship onboarding</title><link href="https://www.juanelosua.com/posts/event/onboarding/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2015-01-20T13:20:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Juan Elosua</name></author><id>tag:www.juanelosua.com,2015-01-20:posts/event/onboarding/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;2015 is starting and as a new Knight-Mozilla fellows I joined the rest of the cohort in the onboarding event in Los Angeles. I am very grateful to Dan, Erika, Ryan and Erin (in spirit) for giving us the opportunity to get to know the rest of the fellows in more depth both personally and professionally.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This fellowship is one of a kind in the sense that each one of us is going to be headed to a different newsroom so this event was a good opportunity to establish relationships that will be kept during 2015 but mainly through remote channels.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this post I will try to share with you my impressions of the event where we have received tons of information and were able to work together in an open source project started by the &lt;a href="http://www.californiacivicdata.org/"&gt;California Civic Data Coalition&lt;/a&gt; that tries to provide a better understanding of campaign finance in the state of California.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;h2 id="day-1-jan-12th"&gt;Day 1 (Jan 12th)&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To start the onboarding event we went to &lt;a href="http://www.thehubla.com/"&gt;The Hub LA&lt;/a&gt;, Two former fellows &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/brianabelson"&gt;Brian Abelson&lt;/a&gt; (2013) and &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/auremoser"&gt;Aurelia Moser&lt;/a&gt; (2014) joined us and share their experiences and tips with us. It was really important to listen to their advices since they are the best counsellors that we could have having lived the same situations that we are going to have this year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some of their recommendations were:
&lt;em&gt; Try to stay as organized as possible
&lt;/em&gt; Have a fluent communication about your interests and schedule with your point of contact in the newsroom
* Conferences are great but this fellowship is in no way a one-shot opportunity so try to select the ones that will be more profitable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We were also fed with a full plate of information from the opennews staff regarding logistics, policies, community and how to work in the open sharing the experience as one of the main goals of the fellowship.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;h2 id="day-2-jan-13th"&gt;Day 2 (Jan 13th)&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="LATimes visit" class="post_left" src="/images/onboarding/LAtimes.jpg" width="50%" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We visited the LA Times newsroom guided by &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/palewire"&gt;Ben Welsh&lt;/a&gt;. We shamelessly interrupted some journalists and got the chance to ask them questions regarding their work and their relationship with the Data Desk that Ben leads at the newsroom. It was really an interesting visit where we got the sense of the work that each of us will be doing at our host newsroom.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Data journalism seems to be a brand new thing but we have learned from people in the LA times that data related investigations have been done since the 80s...of course with different tools but we are not reinventing the wheel, the challenges and workflows of data investigations apply the same now as they did back then.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="clear_float"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;h2 id="day-3-jan-14th"&gt;Day 3 (Jan 14th)&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We went to USC to begin our two hackdays on the &lt;a href="http://django-calaccess-campaign-browser.californiacivicdata.org/en/latest/"&gt;CAL-ACCESS campaign browser&lt;/a&gt; project. Ben Welsh and &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/aboutaaron"&gt;Aaron Williams&lt;/a&gt; from the CIR gave us an overview of the project goals and the tasks that they had in mind for our contribution to the project.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="USC campaign-browser hackday" class="post_right" src="/images/onboarding/hackday.jpg" width="50%" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The campaign browser is an ongoing project that aims at helping journalists and other interested persons in improving their way of extracting meaningful information out of  the &lt;a href="http://cal-access.ss.ca.gov/default.aspx"&gt;CAL-ACCESS&lt;/a&gt; data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We had tasks that were oriented towards frontend as well as backend improvements.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since I am more comfortable in backend tasks, &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/frnsys"&gt;Francis&lt;/a&gt;, Ben and I started working on a scraper ran as a custom django-admin command that will complement the information dump that the secretary of state publishes on a daily basis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We wanted to be able to answer some questions that believe it or not were not possible to answer without that scraping task from the original dump, for example: How much money was spent in campaign finance for each election?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also we wanted to be able to link each ballot measure with their supporting/opposing committees and we wrote a second scraper to do that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="tech-tip-of-the-day"&gt;Tech tip of the day&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you have not used Django models before there is one nice feature that I will try to point out when building many-to-many relationships in a Django model.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In our example a &lt;em&gt;propostition/ballot measure&lt;/em&gt; can have many &lt;em&gt;committees&lt;/em&gt; associated with but that works reversely also a &lt;em&gt;committee&lt;/em&gt; can support/oppose to many &lt;em&gt;propositions&lt;/em&gt;. In relational databases this is known as a many-to-many relationship.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Django allows you to model that with a &lt;a href="https://docs.djangoproject.com/en/1.7/topics/db/examples/many_to_many/"&gt;ManyToManyField&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When creating the model using the migrate command, Django under the hood will create a table in the Database for the relationship between &lt;em&gt;proposition&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;committee&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span class="nv"&gt;$ &lt;/span&gt;python manage.py migrate
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;But what if we wanted to characterize that relationship with some attribute as is the case in out example. We don't want just the relationship between a &lt;em&gt;proposition&lt;/em&gt; and a &lt;em&gt;committee&lt;/em&gt; we want to know also if the &lt;em&gt;commitee&lt;/em&gt; is supporting or opposing to the &lt;em&gt;proposition&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We can do that in Django by providing a &lt;em&gt;through&lt;/em&gt; model to the ManyToManyField (In CAL-ACCESS a committee is identified by a Filer). Now we can explicitly create the relationship model.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span class="k"&gt;class&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nc"&gt;Proposition&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;BaseModel&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;):&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="n"&gt;name&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;models&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;CharField&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;max_length&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;255&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;null&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="bp"&gt;True&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="n"&gt;filer_id_raw&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;models&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;IntegerField&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;db_index&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="bp"&gt;True&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="c"&gt;#&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="n"&gt;election&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;models&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;ForeignKey&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;Election&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;null&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="bp"&gt;True&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;default&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="bp"&gt;None&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="hll"&gt;    &lt;span class="n"&gt;filers&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;models&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;ManyToManyField&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;Filer&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;through&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;&amp;#39;PropositionFiler&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Take a look at the PropositionFiler class that models the relationship. We need to provide at least the keys that will relate the two models in our case &lt;em&gt;proposition&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;filer&lt;/em&gt; (When not using a through model this would be what django will create under the hood). But now check the position field where we can characterize the relationship with a support or oppose stating whether the committee (filer) opposes/supports the related proposition.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span class="k"&gt;class&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nc"&gt;PropositionFiler&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;BaseModel&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;):&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="n"&gt;POSITION_CHOICES&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;&amp;#39;SUPPORT&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s"&gt;&amp;#39;Support&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;),&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;&amp;#39;OPPOSE&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s"&gt;&amp;#39;Oppose&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;),&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="hll"&gt;    &lt;span class="n"&gt;proposition&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;models&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;ForeignKey&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;Proposition&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="hll"&gt;    &lt;span class="n"&gt;filer&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;models&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;ForeignKey&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;Filer&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;    &lt;span class="n"&gt;position&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;models&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;CharField&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class="n"&gt;choices&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;POSITION_CHOICES&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class="n"&gt;max_length&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;50&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;You can use a through model in a many-to-many relationship each time you need to qualify our characterize that relationship with some attributes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can read more about the through option in the awesome django documentation &lt;a href="https://docs.djangoproject.com/en/1.7/topics/db/models/#intermediary-manytomany"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="clear_float"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;h2 id="day-4-jan-15th"&gt;Day 4 (Jan 15th)&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After a successful scrape we cleaned up the code a little bit, document it and pushed the changes. I have not been involved in large open source projects with more than 3 or 4 developers so this was a good opportunity to grasp important ideas related to documentation and workflows needed to keep a distributed open source project running smoothly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ben, shared with us his vision on the &lt;em&gt;Documentation Driven Development&lt;/em&gt; which I thought was a nice advise to push open source projects forward instead of what Dan mentioned to be &lt;em&gt;source available&lt;/em&gt; projects. I certainly need to progress on this myself and that is one of the challenges I will be facing during this fellowship year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I switched to some frontend task to help &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/taraandtheworld"&gt;Tara&lt;/a&gt; figure out how to handle a visualization that uses &lt;a href="http://dc-js.github.io/dc.js/"&gt;dc.js&lt;/a&gt;. DC.js is a javascript charting library with native &lt;a href="http://square.github.io/crossfilter/"&gt;Crossfilter&lt;/a&gt; support allowing highly efficient exploration on large multi-dimensional dataset. It leverages &lt;a href="http://d3js.org/"&gt;D3&lt;/a&gt; engine to render charts in css friendly svg format.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="DC.js library" class="post_full_nb" src="/images/onboarding/dc.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you want to get started with dc.js I found this four part &lt;a href="http://www.codeproject.com/Articles/693841/Making-Dashboards-with-Dc-js-Part-Using-Crossfil"&gt;tutorial&lt;/a&gt; easy to follow when I try to figure out how to use that library...Trust me give it a chance...you will love it!!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="clear_float"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;h2 id="summary"&gt;Summary&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="github activity" class="post_right_nb" src="/images/onboarding/commits.png" width="50%" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Overall the onboarding event was a great experience, we got to work together as a cohort and shared our strong and weak points with the rest. I feel now more comfortable to work together, share our knowledge and collaborate in some projects during this amazing year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To end this post I will like to thank &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/dansinker"&gt;Dan&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/erika_owens"&gt;Erika&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/ryanpitts"&gt;Ryan&lt;/a&gt; for their support and openness...you make everybody feel welcomed and challenged to keep growing the awesome data journalism tech community out there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="clear_float"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="USC fellows" class="post_full" src="/images/onboarding/fellows.jpg" width="70%" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="opennews"></category></entry></feed>